NARRATOR:
Hear now the song of Troy,
and of the years
the sea would not forget.
Long ago, the kingdoms
of Greece united
in a common cause...
summoned by oath and honor.
Their kings gathered
a mighty fleet
and sailed across the sea
to the great city of Troy.
Its walls higher
than any siege tower,
thick enough that no battering
ram could break them.
A city that should
never have fallen.
At its heart was Helen, wife
of Menelaus, king of Sparta,
and when the Trojan prince
Paris carried her away,
the kingdoms of Greece
arose as one.
For ten long years,
they lay siege to Troy.
Though countless warriors
fought and died,
the city remained unconquered.
But where armies had failed,
cunning would prevail.
Under the cover of darkness,
Odysseus set a daring
plan into motion.
Greek warriors entered
the city unseen.
By dawn, Troy was
consumed by fire,
and the long war
had come to an end.
Yet for Odysseus,
patient as the tide,
and cunning beyond all others,
the longest journey
was just beginning.
The King!
King Odysseus!
Our men are gone,
but Troy is fallen,
and our battle is won.
Where are we going?
Home.
To my kingdom.
To my son. My wife.
You may join me.
Be an advisor
in my court.
For your bravery in this
terrible war, I will ensure
you will want for nothing
for the rest of your life.
Thank you, my King.
It would be my honor.
The journey will not be easy.
I will swim if I must,
but I will get home.
Trojans!
If the gods are willing.
Tell me, O Muse,
the man of many devices,
who wandered full
many ways after he had
sacked the great
citadel of Troy.
Home, then.
Lest I have not honored the gods
enough to receive
the reward I deserve.
Greetings, Odysseus.
The good man.
Bright-eyed Athena.
Goddess on high.
Clever, maybe.
Clever is better than good.
Not just clever.
Brutal, decisive,
and ingenious.
Hiding your soldiers
in the gift of a wooden horse,
your Trojan horse.
Taking the city by surprise
from the inside out.
Your greatest work.
It did what it was made to do.
But I cannot look behind.
As any craftsman
worth his salt, I pray
that my greatest
work lies ahead.
Perhaps it does.
So home, then. Ithaca.
To your wife.
Your city.
Yes, the only
journey worth the fight.
Are you coming with me, Athena?
Or is there another
reason for this visit?
I come to bring you a warning.
The gods,
they are fickle, Odysseus.
They will not make your
journey home an easy one.
Your trials will be
their entertainment.
They know now that
you are a clever man.
They are jealous.
They will use this against
you to show their power.
Curse me or bless me,
Goddess on high.
But be quick about it.
In due time.
And so begins your odyssey.
And the game of the gods.
Then pray for me, goddess.
For I must reach home.
For my kingdom.
My everything.
My son. My wife.
My world will be gone.
I am looking for men.
A crew for a dangerous journey.
One the gods themselves
may turn their will against.
Once I am home,
as king of Ithaca,
I assure you each will
receive a suitable reward.
You will never want for anything
for the rest of your lives.
You have the word
of the king himself.
A generous offer and reward.
But are you as
good as your word?
Polites!
You look a little
bit past your prime.
- By the gods!
- Old man.
After all this time.
All this time and you still
haven’t gotten any better
at motivational speeches.
Absolute crickets
from you as well.
This is a man who has saved
my life on numerous occasions.
A debt we have both repaid
each other more than once
in a war that has lasted
more than five years.
Although it’s closer to ten now.
But these days,
I am much better collecting
scars than I am glory.
But, you will find plenty
of much younger,
probably not as bright men
more than willing to join you.
But probably not here,
sipping goblets in
the middle of the day.
And the rest here,
well, they know not
the true cost of war,
though they may be eager.
- As once we were.
- As we once were.
Listening to our fathers
and our grandfathers stories.
And just more than
willing to prove ourselves.
Can I trust them?
About as much as
you can trust me.
All I know is that what’s
waiting for you back in Ithaca,
now that is your reward.
And you deserve it, too.
But for the rest of us...
Join me.
I need men who I can trust.
Men with
experience in battle.
No, no, no. I will not be
going to any battle.
Or any wars.
Ever again.
I am unpersuadable.
I cannot be persuaded.
Did I mention the gold?
Well, did I mention
unpersuaded?
When do we start?
As soon as we recruit two more.
- Two more?
- Yes.
Okay. Let’s go.
Alkimos the Navigator.
From what I heard, he was
the one that saved a ship
of fishermen from a cyclone.
Really?
I’ve heard of you,
King Odysseus.
What have you heard?
That you, sacker of cities,
son of Laertes,
are favored by the gods.
Not all the gods.
One or two. Maybe less.
You survived the Trojan War.
You’re a king.
The King of Ithaca.
I have a family
that comes from Ithaca.
I haven’t seen them
since I was little.
You know, my king--
I’m not king today.
But if you help me
get home, I will be.
I’m a good navigator.
But you mentioned gold.
Did I?
Oh. You did. Yes.
You mentioned gold.
He mentioned gold.
Hmm.
I don’t seek gold.
I’m bored.
Bored of fishing
boats filled with old men
with putrid smelling cargo.
I seek adventure.
New shores.
Like in the stories.
Stories about you.
Then join me,
and we will make stories
that they will never forget.
And I promise you, it will
be anything but boring.
And once we reach Ithaca,
you can join my guard
and help me protect
our fair kingdom.
My king.
Now, how are you at fighting?
I can handle my own.
But if you want a
force to be reckoned with,
you want to
recruit Eurylochus,
I’ve never seen another
man fight quite like he has.
We’ll pay him a visit next.
So what say you, Eurylochus?
I have killed a lot of
men to protect my home.
War has plagued our
country for many years.
How are you at sea?
I’m a fast swimmer, and
even faster with a sword.
Hm. Is that so?
Hm.
But now that
the war is over,
I’ve found work at a
vineyard up the road.
The owner, he treats me well.
And his daughter,
Talia, she’s...
I just don’t know if I can
commit to a journey this long.
You will be in Ithaca
before sundown two days hence.
We have to be.
And if you decide to
stay in our fair kingdom,
you will live a life
of ease in Ithaca.
And once there,
she can join you.
If you teach me
how to be as fast
as you, my king
Odysseus, then I’m in.
And as I promised...
We need gold.
You said we need to
be to Ithaca in two days.
Yes. I have a plan.
But you must trust me.
I’m with you to
the end, my king.
Or thereabouts.
From Troy, Odysseus
launched his journey home
with 12 ships and 600 men.
Back in Ithaca,
Odysseus’s dear wife Penelope
dreams of her love
bearing the brutal seas
to find his way home to her.
Odysseus?
God’s above.
You’ve shown me Odysseus lives.
Now bring him home.
Bring him home now,
or these lips
shall never again
speak your names.
A growing boy needs food.
A boy needs many things,
mother, but I am not a boy.
Not any...
Mother.
I’ve seen him, Telemachus.
I’ve seen your father.
You’re bleeding.
You must sit.
No, my son.
We must stand and fight.
What have you seen?
A vision.
A message from the gods.
Troy burns.
Your father, he is triumphant.
He is coming home, but it
may not be fast enough.
Ithaca is vulnerable now.
Now that the war is over,
Odysseus must return to
reclaim the throne, otherwise
another can claim this
kingdom as his own.
Your father would rather
die than let that happen.
He will return.
He must.
And in his absence,
I am the man of this house,
and I say that we...
You will be a man
soon enough, my love. You will.
But you cannot be king.
Not yet.
And therein lies our fight.
Each day that your father
is away, others become
more willing to claim
this kingdom as their own.
If he does not return,
I will not also lose you.
So we must be strong, my son.
Together, we must
be like your father.
Smart and resourceful.
And protect this
kingdom without violence.
Clever.
So clever as to make
the gods jealous.
Whether we want it or not,
the heavens will continue to
move without Odysseus here
by our side where he belongs.
If he does not return soon
after victory
has been declared,
then by law he will have
abandoned his duties as king.
And a suitor, any suitor,
may lay claim to this house,
and to the crown of Ithaca.
And to you.
The law only reaches so far.
When they come,
and come they will,
we must be ready.
And I am ready to fight for you
and for father and the kingdom.
Son, this is not going
to be a sword fight.
Or even a fight of fists.
This will be a fight
of words and propriety.
We need to buy him time.
Keep the suitors busy.
Their bellies full
and distracted.
Now come and honor me
like you do him.
The war is over now.
But our battle
is just beginning.
Goddess Athena...
Help us.
I pray.
But help Odysseus.
Help my father.
Please.
The mighty storm
that struck Odysseus
ravaged the sea for ten days,
taking them far off course.
After battling the sea,
Odysseus has arrived
at his home in Ithaca...
or so he thought.
This is not Ithaca, Athena!
This is another one
of the gods’ cruel jokes.
I must get home.
I will get home.
Penelope.
Sweet Penelope.
I will come home.
Look at you keeping
step with the gods.
Athena.
I am many leagues off course.
I’m only two days
journey from Ithaca.
Please.
Spirit me home to Ithaca,
great goddess.
You know that I cannot.
It is not within
my power to do so.
But think, Odysseus.
Perhaps there is a reason
that you are not yet home.
The gods have another plan.
I see.
I am here to help.
I can offer you help three
times along your journey.
Three gifts.
Only three?
’Tis all I am permitted.
I am helping because
I see myself
in your clever mind and
your tactician’s brain.
Your glory in
the Trojan War honors me.
And that is why I will help you.
I am flattered, goddess.
I must decline.
I am offended.
Odysseus.
Refusing a gift from the gods?
From Athena herself.
If you cannot spirit
me home then please
understand I must ask for
help only when I need it.
When all hope is lost, my wits
abandon me and death beckons.
In this moment I will
honor your generosity
for I know the
value of godly gifts.
Then you must know even now
dogs are sniffing
at your house
and at your wife.
The gods are testing
your cleverness, Odysseus.
Then I pray the
gods do not stall me
any longer than
they already have.
Go, hero.
Honor me and prove your worth.
Get home.
No matter what horrors the
gods place upon your path.
The opportunity here
is too great to pass up.
A kingdom, a crown,
and even the queen herself
all free for the taking.
And it should be easy
enough owing to propriety
and Grecian law.
All suitors
must be taken seriously.
And I will be the first.
Ha!
The early bird gets the kingdom.
She’ll have no choice
but to honor my demands.
All of my demands.
Antinous just said
the most awful things.
Threatening to take the crown,
our house, and you!
Then it has begun.
We must be on our
guard, Telemachus.
Always polite and inviting.
But on our guard.
But on our guard!